<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    R Service Bus
    
    Copyright (c) Copyright of Open Analytics NV, 2010-2014
 
    ===========================================================================
 
    This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
    it under the terms of the GNU Affero General Public License as published by
    the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
    (at your option) any later version.
 
    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    GNU Affero General Public License for more details.
 
    You should have received a copy of the GNU Affero General Public License
    along with this program.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>
        
    @author rsb.development@openanalytics.eu
-->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Scalability</title>
    <author email="rsb.development@openanalytics.eu">RSB Development</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Scalability">
      <subsection name="Scaling Up">
        <p>The workload of single RSB instance is expected to be minimal, as the
          bulk of the computation is performed by RServi while RSB takes care of
          moving job requests and results between JMS, file system and e-mail
          destinations.</p>
        <p>Increasing the processing throughput of a single RSB node can be
          achieved by increasing the size of the RServi node pool and the number
          of RSB workers. Alternatively, if a single RServi instance is reaching
          a limit that prevents adding more nodes, RSB can be configured to
          connect multiple RServi instances in order to spread the workload
          across them. The selection of a particular pool could be achieved by
          assigning each independent RSB worker to a specific RServi node or by
          using the configurable association between applications and RServi
          pools (for example, to dispatch process intensive applications to a
          specific RServi pool).</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Scaling Out">
        <p>Currently, RSB is architectured to run as a single stand-alone node.
          Should it become necessary to run several nodes in parallel, the
          following must be considered:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <i>RSB polls email resources</i>
            : running several instances concurrently
            consuming the same inboxes
            would create issues, as some jobs could
            potentially be retrieved
            several times (an email resource is not
            transactional). A possible
            mitigation is to configure each node
            differently so they don't
            compete for the same inboxes.<br/><br/>
          </li>
          <li>
            <i>RSB uses the local file system for handling multi-file jobs</i>
            : if several RSB nodes get connected to a single JMS provider
            (instead of each of them using an embedded one), it is possible that
            a JMS message carries a pointer that references a file present in the
            file system of another node. A possible mitigation consists in
            carrying the full multi-file job payloads in JMS messages instead of File
            references.<br/><br/>
          </li>
          <li>
            <i>Results for the REST API are stored in the local file system:</i>
            in order to have several RSB nodes serve the same results either the
            file system where the results are stored should be shared across
            machines (like with an NFS mount) or an alternative implementation of
            <a href="apidocs/index.html?eu/openanalytics/rsb/data/ResultStore.html">ResultStore</a>
            that allows sharing over the network (for example a DB or Redis backed implementation).
            <br/><br/>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>